{
  "reference_number": "12309",
  "clauses": [
    {
      "question": "1. What process should the Government use to set a new emissions reduction target in legislation?",
      "question_index": 0,
      "answer": "The Government sets a goal to reach net zero emissions by the second half of the century and the Climate Change Commission advises on the specific target for the Government to set later",
      "answer_index": 11,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The Global Warming and Climate Change Mitigation and Adaptation Bill (see my recommendation in the\n ‘additional notes’ section at the end of this submission) should set a goal of net zero greenhouse gas emissions by 2050. That goal\n\n must be fixed and the Bill should prohibit it being changed (unless someone would like to suggest that we actually start trying to\n return to pre-industrial levels of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere). Otherwise, as 2050 approaches, it could be too easy to\n\n modify the goal if the adaptation had not been progressing as planned in relation to the emission budgets. The Climate Change\n Commission would advise Parliament and make recommendations about the interim 5-yearly annual greenhouse gas emission\n budgets."
    },
    {
      "question": "2. If the Government sets a 2050 target now, which is the best target for New Zealand?",
      "question_index": 1,
      "answer": "Net Zero Emissions - Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050",
      "answer_index": 1,
      "notes": "The answer depends upon the definition of the word ‘best’. The best target for the New Zealand economy in the short term would\n\n be the first option, “Not specified”. The best target for the environment which sustains life, including humans, would be the fourth\n option, “Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050.” RECOMMENDATION: The Bill should propose the fourth option,\n\n “Net zero emissions across all greenhouse gases by 2050.” RECOMMENDATION: The language should always use the term “net\n zero greenhouse gas emissions”."
    },
    {
      "question": "3. How should New Zealand meet its targets?",
      "question_index": 2,
      "answer": "Domestic emissions reductions only (including from new forest planting)",
      "answer_index": 7,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The New Zealand ETS is susceptible to corruption. To help ensure that the ETS is not used ‘inappropriately’,\n Parliament must ensure that the New Zealand ETS be used only within New Zealand so that all aspects of its transactions can be\n\n regulated and monitored, and that no international carbon credits be purchased to offset greenhouse gas emissions in New Zealand."
    },
    {
      "question": "4. Should the Zero Carbon Bill allow the 2050 target to be revised if circumstances change?",
      "question_index": 3,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: Global warming and climate change are reasonably well understood. It is extremely unlikely that circumstances\n will change for the better. If there’s a change, it will probably be only for the worse. There are two circumstances in which the Bill\n\n should allow the target to be changed and only to make it more demanding: (1) reduce the levels of greenhouse gas emissions only\n if Parliament can agree that we should actually start trying to return to pre-industrial levels of greenhouse gases in the atmosphere, or\n (2) that the target date of 2050 be brought closer. Easing the target by increasing the allowable amount of greenhouse gas\n\n emissions to be reduced or increasing the year of the target should be prohibited."
    },
    {
      "question": "5. The Government proposes that three emissions budgets of five years each (i.e. covering the next 15 years) be in place at any given time. Do you agree with this proposal?",
      "question_index": 15,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The 5-yearly budgets should be explicitly stated in annual increments so that our progress towards the target,\n\nor otherwise, can be regularly monitored and reported to Parliament on an annual basis."
    },
    {
      "question": "6. Should the Government be able to alter the last emissions budget (i.e. furthest into the future)?",
      "question_index": 4,
      "answer": "Yes - the third emissions budget should be able to be changed but only when the subsequent budget is set",
      "answer_index": 4,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: No emissions budget should be able to be increased, only decreased."
    },
    {
      "question": "7. Should the Government have the ability to review and adjust the second emissions budget within a specific range under exceptional circumstances? See p36 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 5,
      "answer": "No",
      "answer_index": 8,
      "notes": "Considering that ‘exceptional circumstances’ occur from time to time, and will continue to occur during and after the ‘special period’\n\nof mitigation and adaptation, the existential threat of global warming and climate change demands that we not excuse ourselves for\nwithdrawing in any way in our continuous efforts to mitigate and adapt to the consequences of global warming and climate change."
    },
    {
      "question": "8. Do you agree with the considerations we propose that the Government and the Climate Change Commission take into account when advising on and setting budgets? See p44 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 6,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: If reference is made to \"our obligations under the Treaty of Waitangi\", those obligations must be specifically and\nfully described, not left as a vague phrase with no definite meaning."
    },
    {
      "question": "9. Should the Zero Carbon Bill require Governments to set out plans within a certain timeframe to achieve the emissions budgets?",
      "question_index": 7,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The Government should provide the New Zealand population with information about its intended policies, plans,\nand procedures to meet the emissions budgets with as much advance notice (warning) as possible. It should also devise ways for\n\nthe changes to be absorbed by everyone in New Zealand as easily as possible with the least amount of disruption, to assist everyone\nto plan for and adjust to the intended changes. For example, it would be better to increase petrol prices starting immediately by 2\n\ncents per litre per week (that is, an increase of 2 cents each successive week) than by stating that its intention would be to increase\npetrol prices by $2 per litre in 2021."
    },
    {
      "question": "10. What are the most important issues for the Government to consider in setting plans to meet budgets? For example, who do we need to work with, what else needs to be considered?",
      "question_index": 8,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "The Government needs to consult with anyone who might have information about how best to meet the budgets, how best to\n\nschedule the changes required, and how best to engage the public so that they strive to meet the budget fairly, efficiently, and\neffectively within the necessary time frames."
    },
    {
      "question": "11. The Government has proposed that the Climate Change Commission advises on and monitors New Zealand's progress towards its goals. Do you agree with these functions? See p42 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 9,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: Because it is critical that almost all if not all of New Zealand’s population understand the threat of global warming\nand consequent climate change, understand the existential need and the means to constrain and reduce global warming,\n\nunderstand the effects and impacts that constraining and reducing global warming will have on our New Zealand society, and\nunderstand the critical need to maintain civil society and how to achieve that while undergoing all the required changes to our society\n\nand its cultures, the Commission should be instructed to establish and provide an aggressive educational program for all New\nZealanders of all ages starting immediately upon its establishment. As well, the Commission should be authorised to establish\n\nvarious measures and means to statistically monitor the desired effects of its educational program. Recommendation: The\nCommission should have the following functions: (1) advise the Government about its 2050 emissions target, its 5-yearly annual\n\nemissions budgets, and means of mitigation and adaptation (2) establish measures and statistically monitor all emissions so that it\ncan accurately report to the Government New Zealand’s progress meeting the 2050 emissions target and 5-yearly annual emissions\nbudgets, (3) enforce with Parliamentary authorisation any mandatory emissions regulations, with the power of exacting fines from any\n\nindividuals or organisations not complying with the regulations, and (4) educating the public about global warming and climate\nchange in order to promote civil health and security."
    },
    {
      "question": "12. What role do you think the Climate Change Commission should have in relation to the New Zealand Emissions Trading Scheme (NZ ETS)?",
      "question_index": 10,
      "answer": "Advising the Government on policy settings in the NZ ETS",
      "answer_index": 6,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: Because the ETS should not be used to allow anyone or any organisation to permanently deflect their\n\nresponsibility to reduce their greenhouse gas emissions, the Commission should be instructed to recommend to the Government 5-\nyearly emissions budgets to annually reduce the amount of emissions traded by the ETS with the intended target being to eliminate\nthe ETS by at least 2040. As well, the Commission should be authorised to establish various measures and means to statistically\n\nmonitor the desired decrease in the use of the ETS."
    },
    {
      "question": "13. The Government has proposed that Climate Change Commissioners need to have a range of essential and desirable expertise. Do you agree with the proposed expertise? See p45 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 11,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: As well, because of the need for the Commission to educate the public, one or more of its members should\nhave established educational credentials, expertise, and a history of experience in public education."
    },
    {
      "question": "14. Do you think the Zero Carbon Bill should cover adapting to climate change?",
      "question_index": 12,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: Because neither the emission budgets nor the 2050 target will be met without the New Zealand society\nadapting its culture and economy during the intervening years, the Commission should be instructed to advise the Government\n\nabout the optimal scheduling and means of achieving the adaptations needed to achieve the emission budgets and the 2050 target."
    },
    {
      "question": "15. The Government has proposed a number of new functions to help us adapt to climate change. Do you agree with the proposed functions? See p47 Our Climate Your Say",
      "question_index": 13,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The Commission should be responsible for (1) coordinating all scientific and technical enquiry into the matter of\nglobal warming and climate change adaptation and advising the Government accordingly, (2) regular national climate change risk\nassessment reports, (3) a national adaptation plan, with a 2050 target and 5-yearly budgets, including the means to measure and\n\nmonitor the implementation and progressive achievement of that plan, and (5) a national adaptation enforcement power (see\nquestion 16)."
    },
    {
      "question": "16. Should we explore setting up a targeted adaptation reporting power that could see some organisations share information on their exposure to climate change risks?",
      "question_index": 14,
      "answer": "Yes",
      "answer_index": 3,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: The Commission should be provided with the authority to establish regulations for individuals and organisations\n\nto report any or all data relevant to their emissions and appropriate to the national measurement of emissions, and the authority to\nenforce that reporting, including the power to fine individuals and organisations."
    },
    {
      "question": "Do you have any other comments you'd like to make?",
      "question_index": 16,
      "answer": null,
      "answer_index": 5,
      "notes": "RECOMMENDATION: Because the proposed name of this bill, namely the Zero Carbon Act, does not clearly or fully describe the\nconcern or the nature of this bill (firstly, nitrous oxide and water vapour are also greenhouse gases but do not contain carbon, and\n\nsecondly, the intent is not to emit zero carbon in greenhouse gases, which would probably be not only impossible but actually lethal\nto all plant life and subsequently all life including human life if achieved), the bill should be renamed the Global Warming and Climate\n\nChange Mitigation and Adaptation Act. If that RECOMMENDATION is not acceptable, at least call it the “Net Zero Carbon Act”.\nRECOMMENDATION: Because of the existential threat of global warming and climate change, the New Zealand Parliament should\nestablish the Zero Carbon Act (or Net Zero Carbon Act, or preferably the Global Warming and Climate Change Mitigation and\n\nAdaptation Act) as ‘entrenched’ legislation requiring at least a 75% majority for amendment or repeal. As well, the Act should prohibit\nthe amendment of the clause expressing the 2050 net zero greenhouse gas emissions target. The vote should be a conscience\n\nvote not subject to political party voting rules and procedures (whipping). This recommendation is intended to reduce significantly\nthe effect of the three-year electoral term with its consequential yo-yoing of political party policy changes. RECOMMENDATION: The\n\nZero Carbon Act (preferably named the Global Warming and Climate Change Mitigation and Adaptation Act), or “the Act”, should\ncontain clauses requiring all other subsequent legislation to comply with the Act so that, after it has become law, it will be one of the\nlegal foundations of our society, like the electoral law and the human rights law. Accordingly, separate adaptation acts for various\n\nsectors of the economy could be enacted having legal subordination to the Act.\nSubject: Fwd: Thank you for making a submission\n\nRecipient: zero-carbon-bill@submissions.mfe.govt.nz\n\n\nSender: ZCB.Submissions@mfe.govt.nz\n\nDate: 24/07/2018 10:36 PM\n\n\nGood day,\n\nI would like the following remarks added to my submission, reference number 12309.\n\n  1.\n      The\n\n       Climate Change Commission\n\n\n\n        a.\n           It\n            must be independent and non-poitical.\n\n\n        b.\n           It\n\n            must be fully funded.\n\n        c.\n\n           It\n            must monitor the reality of the New Zealand environment using scientifically accepted measures.\n\n\n        d.\n           It\n\n            must regularly advise the Government about what is needed to address this existential threat without any\n           political bias.\n\n\n        e.\n           It\n            must act as an educational agent to advise the New Zealand public about the existential crisis all humanity\n\n           faces.\n\n\n\n  2.\n      Net\n       zero emission by 2050\n\n\n\n        a.\n\n           This\n            goal is not sufficiently aspirational. I believe the goal should be zero fossil carbon extraction for energy and net\n\n           zero greenhouse gases by 2050 and zero carbon credits by 2040.\n\n\n\n  3.\n      Electric\n       cars, solar panels, and wind turbines are not currently manufactured with zero carbon energy. We need to redesign all\n\n      products to use zero carbon energy in their manufacture.\n\n\nThank you for considering this request.\n\nCheers, Carl Horn\n\n\nCarl Horn\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n\n---------- Forwarded message ----------\n\nFrom: Submissions <noreply@datacomcep.co.nz                >\nDate: 19 July 2018 at 15:53\nSubject: Thank you for making a submission\n\nTo:\nDear Carl Willoch Ludwig Horn\n\n\nYour submission to Zero Carbon Bill has been sent to Ministry for the Environment.\n\nA copy of your submission has been attached to this email.\n\n Submission reference number: 12309"
    }
  ]
}
